- Hey folks, and welcome to
the Learn UI Design lesson
on the color gray.
So I'd like to start by saying
I'm dressed for the occasion.
The color gray, the only
color worth it's own video,
is actually the most important color
in all of user interface design.
And the reason why that is,
is because in this video,
like in the entire
course, when I say gray,
I'm talking about white
and black inclusive.
White, black and every shade
of gray in between them.
That's what makes up gray.
That's really the only
logical way to view it
as far as a UI designer is concerned.
Now, gray is the most important color
that you're going to be using.
Not only is it by far
the most common color,
but it's also the only color
that doesn't really call
attention to itself.
You put some red on the interface
and you're calling attention
to that red in a special way.
Yellow, same thing.
Even blue, blue is a little bit more chill
but gray is really the backseat.
It just kinda, let someone
else do the driving
and the grabbing the attention,
and gray is just there to
transmit the information
that you need to transmit but
not to attract any attention.
It does it very subtly.
It's the quiet professional, okay?
so we're going to be
talking about graying,
all throughout this video.
Just to give you kind of an
overview of how this unit
is put together.
We started by talking
about HSB, hue, saturation,
and brightness.
That HSB way of naming and
modifying colors is foundational
to the learn UI design color
system that I am teaching you.
From HSB, we then talked
about this all-important
fourth property, luminosity,
which is related to hue,
related to saturation,
related to brightness,
but different than all three of those.
And with that knowledge,
we're actually gonna go to,
very soon from here, it's not
this lesson, but very soon,
the keystone lesson of this unit,
which is on making color adjustments.
You have one base color
and using your knowledge
of luminosity, you can make
variations on that base color
as you need.
But, what I want to kind
of hit home in this lesson
is the idea that color is
actually a little bit more
like the toppings on a pizza.
And it's actually really important
that you get the foundation
of the pizza set first.
The good crust, good cheese, good sauce.
It's like, you could have great basics
and that's a pizza just by itself.
But if you ruin those basics,
good toppings aren't gonna save it.
I would probably still eat
the pizza, 'cause it's pizza,
but it's not gonna be very good.
And so, the color gray is
really like the solid crust
and cheese and sauce
that goes on the pizza.
It's those foundations
that we really wanna nail.
All right, enough pizza analogies,
let's actually just get started.
All right, so I'm gonna start off
by showing you this
nice little design here.
And this is a concept
from the design El Niño.
As you may intuit, this is not supposed
to be a finalized design,
but one thing that's really cool about it
is even just being some gray
rectangles and gray text,
it looks really, really sharp, I love it.
And it's kind of impressive
that they're able to do this.
It relies totally on the
fundamentals of alignment,
spacing, consistency and things
like using good typography.
Now for we know this was
not some idol exercise here.
This is actually a design that they made
in preparation for the final design,
which is for the news
organization writers,
which you can see here.
And the thing about this is,
this design also looks really awesome.
Those fundamentals are
still here, the alignment,
the consistency and so on, but
with the extra pop of color
from all the imagery and from
some of this colored text
from little things like a highlight next
to some section names,
it just stays looking
really, really sharp.
And so my first big lesson for you
is until you feel very
comfortable with color,
you should try and design a
little bit more like this.
I call this black and white first.
Why not gray first?
I dunno, black and white first
is just a little bit catchier,
but basically the point is,
until you're very confident
with working with color
try and design something
that looks perfectly sharp,
that obeys all that we've already learned
about alignment, consistency, spacing
except it just doesn't
have any color in it yet.
And then once it looks awesome,
go ahead and add in that color,
from the imagery, from the theme color
the little pops of color and so on.
To use the pizza metaphor,
once you have that good crust
and good sauce and good cheese,
then you add on those toppings.
Now, just to set expectations here.
I'm not saying this is required
but this is a very useful thing to do,
until you're actually really
confident about color.
Because in my own experience,
having looked at thousands
of submissions from Learn UI
design students over the years,
I have noticed that color
is one of the easiest things
to mess up if you're a beginning designer.
Beginning designers put in too much color,
too early and it can really
screw with the design.
So, what I want you to do
is hold off on that color
just a little bit.
And we will have future lessons
where we talk about
exactly how to add it in.
But for now we're going to
say how can we get things
looking as good as
possible, just using gray,
and then, once we allow
ourselves to use color
and imagery just really
make that design shine
for the final version.
Now you might be thinking,
hey, wait a second.
You're telling me to not use
like one of the most important
and fundamental things in
design until the very end?
Well, it's not quite so bad.
One of the things I wanna convince you of,
is that a shocking
amount of good UI design
is actually really just
gray, plus imagery,
plus a few pops of color.
If you've never thought about this before
or if you never have
seen a design this way,
it's actually kind of tough to overstate
how important this is.
When you look at this design,
nothing about it seems like
too simplistic, or like
it's just like too minimal
and boring or whatever.
I just, it looks very, very good here.
And yet when I go through and kind of,
look element by element,
it's clear that basically
everything is gray.
A small pop of color for,
I guess this is a title,
for a little section, sort of headline.
Some of this text is filler text
which I don't recommend doing
but you gotta do it occasionally.
Pops of color in the imagery,
little section highlights right here,
it's all gray scale, plus
imagery, plus pops color.
I'll show you another example.
We'll go on over to the
mobile Twitter design here.
This is for iOS.
If I look at this app right here,
I am seeing gray, gray,
gray, purple color,
there's that blue, gray,
imagery from user submitted content,
gray, gray, imagery from
user submitted content.
Same thing with the imagery,
purple color, purple color.
All the rest is gray.
And this is kind of interesting
because it's not like
Twitter is just known
as a totally Spartan interface, right?
Like everyone knows Twitter's
brand color is this blue.
Like you use the product
and you're gonna be
familiar with that.
It's done well, it has a good brand.
It's very solid, but it
stands apart from the brand.
The point is I don't need
to have the blue in there
for this design to work.
If I just strip out all the
imagery and all the popsicolor,
this is a totally functional
design right here.
And if black and white first sounds like
maybe a bit too extreme
of a way to design,
just consider that it's almost obvious
where you're gonna end up
putting color in this design.
You're gonna see it
wherever there's imagery.
You're gonna see it wherever
there's a selected state,
that's a very common
place for pops of color.
So home is selected, search
and alerts and inbox or not.
You're gonna see it in buttons.
That's another super common place.
And to say, hey, we're gonna show a blue
and a badge right here,
that's also really common.
It's just those couple
of decisions that get you
from something totally gray scale,
to something that looks like
a very neat, clean, modern interface.
Now you might be saying, hey, Eric,
you've just kind of shown
me a couple of clean
and simple designs.
Like of course, clean and simple works,
black and white first
because there's really,
they're not using color all
that extensively anyways.
I'm glad you mentioned it.
I want to talk about a
couple other examples
where again when we put on
that lens of a lot of good UI
just being gray scale plus
imagery, plus pops of color,
you're gonna see exactly how it works.
Even in more thoroughly branded sites.
sites that don't have quite as neutral
of a brand to something like
Twitter or the Reuters app.
So here's Semplice, I called
this out in the first unit
as being a very fancy site.
It has a little bit
more of a formal brand.
Look at that Sarah font
and a lot of gray scale
which seems kind of serious
and yet understated.
Again when we count
this dark gray or black,
whatever it is, I think
it's probably a dark gray.
When we count all of
the white and dark gray
as part of that gray spectrum,
we realized that we're
just looking essentially
at a few pops of color.
And I don't even think
there's any imagery here.
Maybe if we play through
this video, we'll see it.
But it's basically pops
of color and gray scale.
And we'll come back at the
end of this video specifically
to the idea of formal and fancy brands
being really well-served
by the color gray.
Here's the techie brand.
This is a design for origin
materials by Brian Powell,
and it's supposed to be kind of technical
and engineering focused and
you know, that kind of thing.
And it's, I mean, super understated here.
You can see, look at these
dots, feel very technical.
Anyhow, as I scroll down,
pops of color are in arrows,
they're in hover states, but
basically everything else here,
is some shade of gray.
It's not a very long page
but my guess is it's exactly
the same story on other pages as well.
Interestingly enough,
not that this is required
but even the imagery is
gray scale on this site.
So there we go.
You could even do a site that's supposed
to look a lot more
technical or scientific,
and you can use gray scale very heavily
with just pops of color and imagery.
Now I think quirky brands are kind of one
of the other quintessential brands
that you need to learn to design for,
and Row 7 Seeds is actually a
really good example of that.
They make kind of these, I
dunno, seeds for vegetables
that are special in some way.
A seed company dedicated to
deliciousness, there we go.
But you can see they really
have this more artistic,
kind of avant-garde take on it,
like row separated by this
huge space and then seven.
That's not, you can tell they're trying
to push kind of how they display things,
make it more interesting
or artsy and so on.
And yet, even on this site,
which does not feel minimalistic per save,
I still see imagery, white
text, so that's gray,
that counts as gray, imagery, gray, gray,
some more imagery, which is interesting
'cause it's not necessarily
just in a rectangle
kind of partitioned off as
one image on the screen,
it's sort of splattered
about but fair enough,
more gray, more gray, more imagery
more of the other imagery,
gray, gray divider lines,
gray big lines here, kind of
a motif echoing what we saw
in the title.
More imagery, more imagery,
and gray, blah, blah,
all the way down.
So consider this, this site, which again
is as busy as anyone would want,
is still just a very basic pattern.
You can break it down to
being gray, plus imagery,
plus just a few pops of color.
And it's probably worth saying
that when I refer to gray
sometimes I do talk about
low saturation colors
as being gray, even if they're technically
kind of an off gray, so to speak.
Like I think there is
some saturation in this.
This does not look flat to me.
And yet for the purposes of this video,
as long as we have something
that's fairly low saturation
like we're effectively
dealing with a gray.
So when we designed
black and white, first,
all I'm saying to do, is
to take out the imagery,
at least at the beginning and
take out the pops of color
and just have that skeleton
of the site underneath.
If you can nail the skeleton,
you're gonna how things look
when you add in the pops of color
and when you add in the beautiful imagery.
Now, one thing worth
mentioning is that we actually
have a word for a design
that's largely done
in black and white and kind
of ignores color and imagery.
And in designer terms,
we call the wireframe.
And if you go to Dribbble
and you search wireframe,
you're gonna find a lot of
things that in my opinion
are too nice to be wireframes.
I'm gonna call them Dribbble wireframe.
See, a wireframe is a
useful tool for designers
because it looks bad.
Here's an example of one
that I did some years back.
It's got like everything
written in Comic Sans
and it's got these overly dark borders
and it's just, it's really
intentionally low fidelity.
And that's for two reasons.
One is it's quicker to design that way
and two, it signals to
viewers that this is not
a final version and you can
suggest drastic sweeping changes
if you want.
Anyone I show it to is not
gonna feel bad about saying,
hey scrap this and do
something totally different
'cause it doesn't look like
I put my heart and soul into this,
but Dribbble wireframes
can be really nice.
And I think that's just kind of the nature
of having a social network for designers
is people only want to upload things
when they look really, really sharp.
But you can think of
these Dribbble wireframes
as being the sort of thing
that we want to get to
with our own black and
white first designs.
You can go look at a lot
of these for inspiration
and they are linked below.
All right, cool.
Now in the interest of staying practical,
I'm actually gonna slide on over,
and we're gonna do a
little bit of an example.
So this is something
that's maybe a bit closer
to a full-on wireframe in
that everything on here
is either the default figma
gray, black, or white.
And we're gonna talk
about different strategies
for sort of using gray in your designs.
In particular, I'm gonna talk
about seven specific techniques,
but I'm gonna touch on
a whole bunch of ideas.
Now keep in mind that I
am starting from a place
where the alignment here looks good.
Everything's well aligned,
the spacing, I think this
looks like great spacing,
consistency wires and it's fine enough
for our purposes right now.
We're just gonna do some
touch up of the design
and as we sort of get all the grays
in this design straightened out,
then you will see what
exactly it looks like
and what sort of
techniques you'll be using
when you design black
and white first yourself.
All right, so the first
technique is something
that you've probably
seen me do a whole bunch
and I call it the opacity technique.
It's just like reducing
the opacity of something
to sort of reduce its importance.
For instance, one place where
you're gonna do that a lot
is when you have non selected elements
and a list here, profiles
is the selected state
but inbox models and net
new are not as important.
So I could do something like
press eight for 80% opacity,
even seven for 70% opacity and it's gonna
make them lighter.
So that way it's much
easier to focus on the one
that's fully dark, as with
like every property in design,
I don't wanna go so light
that these appear kind
of disabled and unclickable
and typically that's around 50%
compared to whatever the full
opacity is that you're using.
Here it kind of looks
like inbox is disabled.
So it's usually in that 70 to
80% range that I like to go.
And Imma do the same
thing for these tabs here.
I can just select all these to seven,
perfect it's looking great.
Another place where you can
kind of reduce some of the pop
or the visual weight of
certain elements is...
I've got this underline under profiles
and yet it's supposed to
kind of compliment profiles
and ultimately what I wanna
do is have it sort of look
like it belongs with this
text, but this is really thick.
This is three pixels thick,
and this text is much thinner.
And so to kind of make up
for its overly beefy thickness here.
I'm gonna make it a little bit lighter.
Check this out.
If I do like 70% here and then zoom out,
it actually feels a little bit
more balanced with profiles.
We talk about this in the icons unit too.
We call it drawing with the same pen.
In this case, the quote
unquote pen that drew this
is much thicker than
the pen that wrote this.
And so I'm gonna make
up for that thickness
by just making a little bit lighter.
There's 60% even.
And that looks fine too.
Another prime candidate for
lightening is little labels
or texts that has
attention grabbing styling
applied to it in some way.
So this profile label on
the top here is bolder
than normal text it's uppercase
and overall I kind want of,
adjust for that extra styling
by making it let's say like 70% opacity.
And I call this slub styling.
Slub means smaller,
lighter uppercase and bold
and lighter refers to
reducing the opacity.
Those four properties
when used in combination
can oftentimes look really, really nice.
I'm gonna do the same thing
with these labels right here.
I could say something
like 70% there and yeah
that looks a little bit better to me.
Now, another thing is borders.
In the simplicity lesson,
I talked about borders,
divider lines, subtle background colors.
All of this stuff is sort
of being meta content
or meta elements.
It doesn't tell me something directly.
There there's a border here.
It kind of just describes
that the information
within the border is separate
from the information outside
of the border.
Doesn't directly convey information.
It conveys information about
the content that's in here.
So any sort of meta element like ,
is a prime candidate for
lightening as we discussed
in the simplicity video.
I'm gonna go through, I'm
gonna grab all of these
and I'm just gonna make them
something like 10% opacity.
You can often have them
be very, very light.
And the reason for that
is because they only need
to be kind of visible
enough to signal even subtly
even unconsciously, that the
stuff in here is separate
from the stuff out there.
As long as I can kind of
see that at first glance.
I actually don't need
to worry too much more
about exactly how dark or light these are.
Now, another huge candidate for lightening
is repeated elements.
This is also something we
mentioned briefly in simplicity.
When I have something
like this little bar chart
that's repeated across all
these different elements.
That's nice and if there
was just one chart,
I might leave it quite dark.
But when there's all of
these different charts,
I'm actually gonna
probably reduce the opacity
a little bit here
because it's not supposed
to be the focal point of the page.
I'm gonna find one of
these things when I need
to look at it and I'm gonna
be able to see this chart.
I'm not saying I want it to
be at like 10% opacity here
but it certainly doesn't
need to be pure black.
You know, now when I
make a pure black again,
it looks way too strong.
So even if I do something like, 30% or 40%
in all likelihood, I'm
gonna end up coloring
something like these charts anyways.
So I don't need to fret too much
about the exact shade of gray.
And finally, one other thing
that I really like to lighten
is secondary text.
So when I have kind of this primary text,
secondary text pattern
where the secondary text
is below could be above,
or it could be beside
but in this case, it's below,
it's a little bit smaller
and it's kind of secondary information.
I'm just gonna grab
all of these right here
and bring them down to 70% opacity.
Lot of stuff at 70% opacity on this page.
But I feel like that's
kind of a good go-to range.
It's like your first guests
and you can fail left,
fail right around it
but 70% is often a
fairly good value to use.
Now because I'm talking
about the opacity technique
in particular right here.
I should say that when
you hand over a design
to the developer, I've been asked like,
should I actually tell
them to use this same shade
of it's just black?
Should I have them use
black and 70% opacity,
or should I just direct
them to use the color
that is output when black
is made to be 70% opacity?
And in this case, I mean, we could see
what that would look like, by going here.
And it's four D, four D, four D.
in my opinion it doesn't
matter a whole ton.
I think on my own sites,
I typically will have the base color
have different opacities,
four different versions
of the text.
But one of the reasons that
works or one of the conditions
for it working is this
text test to only appear
on gray backgrounds.
If I have a somewhat
transparent layer of a dark gray
or black, that appears
on a colored background
that can be a little bit
weirder of a combination.
And I might wanna specifically
hand adjust that color.
But if I know that this
text is always gonna appear
on light gray or white,
then I have no problem
saying, yeah just take the
base color black in this case
and make it a lighter variation of that.
The second technique I'm gonna talk about
is called thee just
barely colored technique,
and this whole idea
references the fact that
in the real world, if you look
at a photograph or something
you're almost never going
to be seeing pure black
just like this, bringing
that photograph into figma,
pull up your color picker
and see what colors there're.
And you're gonna notice that
the grays are always saturated
and almost always the darker they go
, the more saturated they get.
Now, it's totally possible to say,
hey, I'm gonna make a site
that just will appear super, super stark
and I'm gonna stick with a
default black, black text.
But, in kind of reference
to the real world
and how color works, and
how our eyes are used
to perceiving things.
A lot of times we will not
include flat totally pure black
in our designs.
And instead we'll sat, we'll make it
a little bit more bright and
a little bit more saturated.
And that's what the just
barely color technique is.
Now, one way that I recommend
doing this, is let's say
I just select all the
layers here, on this screen.
And figma is gonna show me all the colors
of everything that I have selected.
Of course, it's just a
couple of colors right here.
To use the just barely colored technique.
What I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
take all these black layers.
This is gonna reference all the black
and the layers I've selected here.
And I'm gonna go, let's say,
this is our theme color.
I'm just gonna make it a theme color.
Now, obviously this is
not what I wanna do.
Although it looks kind of interesting,
but step one is I'm gonna
start with a theme color
that I wanna saturate in.
And then step two is I'm
gonna set the saturation
and brightness to zero.
So the hue doesn't change.
The hue is still 191.
I'm still looking at kind of
this teal thing right here,
but the saturation and the
brightness are both zero.
Now what I'm gonna do
is I'm just gonna sort
of adjust the brightness up.
If I go too far with it,
it's too light of a design.
And if I don't go far enough,
then it's still just kind
of a flat black.
But I'm gonna bring that brightness up
until I feel like I'm kind of
at a good middle ground here.
So maybe something like in the
25% brightness range is good.
Now step four is I'm
gonna add in saturation
until it's just barely colored.
And this is kind of the
name of the technique.
I'm just gonna add in that saturation
until I feel like I'm just
giving off those subtle vibes
of this teal.
Now it's up to me, how
far I wanna go with this.
I could have some pretty dark
and quite saturated texts
but I think it's almost better to stick
where there's just a hint of color.
And it feels like kind of a good trade-off
between something that is
stayed and boring enough
to be just the text in this business app,
but also just has these subtle vibes
of a cool color coming through.
So I could go, grab this color
here and, maybe I paste it,
and have the opportunity
to make another variation
where the figma gray was.
This time though, I'm going to...
Let's see, start with
black but the brightness
is gonna have to come up much higher here.
So maybe I'll do something
like brightness of 90
would be good here and
then add in a little bit
of saturation because the
brightness is so high.
I don't need to add in
very much saturation.
Remember that from the HSB lesson.
I'll probably just add
in a saturation of three
and call it day there.
Now this technique might sound
kind of strange and useless
but it's actually really common.
And it's something that if you're not used
to designing yourself,
you're probably never gonna notice it.
But if I go to this Twitter example
and I'm just gonna make a square of color,
I'm gonna capture their
theme color in one square.
dark text color right here.
I'm gonna grab their...
Thinner texts color right there.
It's kind of a secondary color.
And let's also get, they've
got this lighter color
for this little dot, dot, right there.
Let's grab all these.
All right, let's check this
out folks, what do we got here?
Hue of 201, that's really the
main thing we're looking at.
What's this?
A hue of 210, that's pretty close.
It's not spot on, but
that's not coincidence.
A hue of 205, that's even
closer, and a hue of 203.
What Twitter has done here,
without us even really noticing,
is they've taken their theme color
and they've, ever so gently
saturated all of the texts
on their whole app with the
hue of that theme color.
Now, this is not to say,
you always have to use the
just barely colored technique
in the hue of your theme color.
You could also have the text be saturated
in some other theme color,
but if you do kind of,
be consistent about this, it's just gonna
have a more subtle, consistent vibe.
And to be fair, not having a
totally harsh black color here.
Instead, we have a
little brightness of 10%
and there's some saturation baked in.
That's just gonna feel a little bit easier
on the eyes than if everything
was just that flat black.
All right, this is maybe a
bit silly, but I'm actually
just going to reduce the
brightness of this a little bit.
So it stands out better
against the background up here.
And from here, we're gonna
move on to our third technique.
The elevation technique.
Gray is a super useful color
for conveying elevation.
And if you've seen the
lighting and shadows video,
none of this is gonna be news to you,
but we'll just kind of work
out some elevation details
in this app right here.
Now let's say because of a
constraint on another page
or the other pages in this
app, we know that we want all
of this body content
to be in its own card.
That sort of separated
from the background.
That is by the way, a
totally realistic thing
to have happen.
I might think, hey this
design looks pretty good,
all by itself but then
because of the constraint
of some other page.
I actually need to adjust it,
such that all of this content
is on a card that otherwise
isn't strictly necessary.
So I'm gonna take this layer.
I'm gonna lock it.
We've got our card, let's move this in.
We'll just move it, something like,
10 pixels in or whatever that was.
This is in 16 already.
I could take my columns,
reduce them there.
So if you've watched the
lighting and shadows video,
this should already be a
little bit frustrating to you
because you should know that
to make something appear
kind of raised up above the
surface of its background.
Like this card should be
compared to this background.
You want to make the
surface as raised up lighter
and the background a little bit darker.
This was kind of an
interesting realization for me
as a beginning designer,
because I just sort of assumed
that even light backgrounds
were almost basically just white
and yet it's not at all
crazy to have let's say
a 97% brightness gray background.
And in fact, you could
probably visit some sites
and not even know that
there's a difference
that the background isn't just pure white.
So that covers the background right there.
Now let's make our card.
We're actually just gonna
bring it to be pure white.
There's nothing that
really needs to be raised
above this card.
So that should work just fine.
But now we have kind of
a weird scenario here
because the background
background is 97% brightness.
And the darker we make
this, the more apparent
the effect is gonna be.
But then we get darker for the background
of these tabs here.
And then we get even
lighter, oh, 98% brightness.
That's not right.
This needs to be pure white.
There we go.
What did I say about not
noticing some of these things.
But the point is we go from this 97
to a slightly darker
color, to then a white
that's even brighter.
And that's not the end of
the world from the context
of this tab control.
I can probably more or less tell
that this tab like floats above,
and it's kind of part of the card element
rather than the background.
But still the more consistent
I can be with higher up colors
being a lighter and lower
down colors being darker.
Even if it's a subtle change,
the better it's gonna look.
So I like this even better.
I could do something
like a 95% brightness,
with this increased brightness.
I have to bring the saturation
down a point though.
But now we're running
into a whole other issue,
and you can see it on the sides here.
And now you can see it on the top too.
These colors are like all
really similar, right?
97% brightness, 95, a 100% brightness.
How like when you look at
them, there's some borders
where when I focus on them,
it's kind of difficult
for my eye because the
colors are so similar
that when I zoom in, it's
maybe not hard to see,
but overall, it just kind
of stresses out your eye
to have to peer so intently to
see where one color deviates
to another color.
And that's why we use
the fourth technique,
which is what I call the border technique.
And all this refers to really,
it's not that ingenious
of a name here is adding borders,
to help your eye distinguish
where subtle color changes happen.
So when I have some subtle
background color change.
I can just add a border and
that's gonna make things
a lot better.
Let's go into stroke here and
I'm gonna grab my default,
kind of dark, dark slate right there.
And I can bring the opacity easily down
to something like 10%.
Again, this is sort of a meta element.
It doesn't need to have
much going on for it
in terms of attracting attention,
but it's just there to
make it a little bit easier
to see where you switch
from that 97% brightness,
group down and 90 and
bounce back up to a hundred.
That's gonna make it way easier
to see where these things are happening.
Likewise, I'm gonna do
something else with this design.
Let's say we kind of isolated these cards
and they were floating here,
and there was a background color.
The cards were floating on,
and have to make them white, one sec.
If I have another background
color change right here
for some reason, then that's
like just one more instance
where adding a border is going
to help make that difference
between the two background
colors, a little more clear.
So I could do that there,
by the way I'm gonna give
these all zero border radius.
This little curved in right there.
You can see that makes that easier to see.
And then of course I could
do the same thing up here,
although I would not want
it to go above the tab.
So we'll bring all of
these things to the front.
There we go.
And overall that looks
a little bit cleaner.
One concern I have as a background though,
is the more of this see, the
more the saturation stands out.
So I'm actually gonna reduce
that saturation even further.
Now we're talking.
So that's the border technique
for background color changes.
Whenever you have a very subtle difference
between one background color
and another background color
and you want to sort of highlight that,
without making the background
colors more different
then just throw a really
thin border in there.
We'll see that in some other examples.
And now that you know about
it, you'll actually start
to notice it everywhere.
The next technique I wanna talk about
is the border technique but
applied to fixing fuzzy shadows.
So again, this is something
that we kind of touched on
in the lighting and shadows unit,
but especially if I go
into pixel mode here.
You can see that there's sort
of this natural transition
of darkness, ignore the saturation here.
If you ignore that this is kind of blue.
You'll notice there's sort
of this natural transition
where it's almost like the difference
between these two pixels, is
the same as between these two,
and so on down the road.
And when that happens,
it can make the border
look a little fuzzy.
And I'm definitely getting this effect.
You're watching a more
compressed video of my screen.
So I dunno if he can see it per save,
but to me the shadow here
looks a little bit fuzzy
and kind of hard to distinguish.
So again, we're just
gonna do that same thing
that we did before and copy
this layer, kind of throw it
at the bottom right here,
press enter (mumbles) edit
these points individually
which is a little annoying.
And let me just zoom in.
I wanna make sure, that
this is coming through here.
We'll go grab the text color.
Perfect, it's way too strong
but something like a 10% opacity,
like that should be enough, let's see.
Maybe not, bump it up to 20.
With 20 you can definitely
see the effect, that's cool.
Now I also would be, remiss not to mention
that you can also solve
this by reducing the opacity
of the shadow.
So, right now, I mean, if
the shadow is really strong
then just making it
lighter, can often solve it
without needing a border.
And of course the other way to fix it
is just to change this color right here.
This is one thing in particular,
but hey you know what,
it's like if this header
is supposed to float
above this background,
I could even make it
lighter than the background.
There we go.
That looks pretty cool by itself too.
Now the sixth technique I wanna talk
about is something that we've
already kind of seen here.
I call it the subtle background technique.
And again, is it really a technique?
It's something that was not obvious
to me as a beginning designer.
I thought when the
background color changed,
you couldn't just go from
a gray of 97 brightness
to a gray of 95 brightness,
to a gray of a hundred brightness,
back down to 95 and so on.
I thought it kind of
had to be big and bold
and in your face.
Betterment.com has a
really nice site design
but when I scroll down
these sections right here
kinda like what I just imagined,
if you're designing a landing page
and you have a different
section, why not go
from blue to green, to gray,
back to blue and whatever.
And even, here's a light gray,
looks like it's gonna
transition into a white
but that's just a card.
And that real transition
is this light gray,
back to the blue and then the
blue back to the dark gray,
the dark gray back to the white.
I mean, these are, with the exception
of this little bit right here.
These are very heavy transitions.
They actually have a very subtle
one at the top right here.
Hey, look at this.
That's our border technique.
But once you know about things
like the border technique
and the subtle background technique,
you can get a lot of
mileage out of like race.
Here's an example, this is Lemonade.com.
There's some things
I'm a little iffy about
on this homepage.
I don't love the font Lato, which they use
and I don't know why
their shadows are pink.
Feels like a little bit
too much is if the buttons
are like emanating out pink light.
Anyhow, in this nice
illustration right here,
you'll notice the horizon
is this light gray.
And the page just stays that light gray,
until what happens, the page
transitions to the white again.
So it's a very light gray,
back to a white, okay?
Now we have another illustration.
The corner of the room here is,
I guess you could call
this the border technique
but then we transitioned
into a light gray.
It stays light gray, for
this section till we need
to change sections and bam,
we're back in white again.
Keep going, here's just one border.
It looks like it's white,
above and below it.
So not really anything crazy right there.
They do another border,
and then they have a light
gray transition right here
with the border technique,
and finally ended with
a much darker header
that just says, hey this
is totally set apart
from the rest of the page,
you're looking at new stuff now.
So that's a perfect example
of the subtle background technique.
We get a lot of mileage out
of just having very subtle
background color changes.
Was also a good demo of
the border technique,
if I do say so myself, thank you Lemonade.
Now we just looked at a
couple of landing pages
but this is actually a
really useful strategy
for apps as well.
So I have a screenshot here,
from the time tracking app harvest,
which I really like and you can see
that a big chunk of this page.
This is actually the same gray 93
above and below this little line here,
half the pages, is just like gray,
and then it transitions
over into a bright white.
Of course this subtle
background color change
is also, accompanied with our favorite
secondary technique here.
The border technique and that
border has a brightness of 80.
All right, now the final
technique I wanna talk about
that you should be using
when you're kind of in
those early pre-color stages
of your design, is the squint test.
And if you've watched this
course straight through
you've heard me talk about
the squint test before.
The squint test just
refers to either squinting
at your design or putting on
a big layer with an effect
of type background blur,
and we'll do something
like 10 pixels of blur and
reduce thee fill opacity
until we get something like
this, we need more blur.
There we go.
Now we were effectively
squinting at our own design here.
And the whole idea, is
just, we want to see
are we effectively corralling
our users' attention?
If someone has just loaded up this page
and they take a half second glance at it.
What sort of information
are they getting out of it?
That's what the squint
test is really useful for.
I can see right here,
definitely have this big title.
I think I would be able to call it.
These are tabs, that this has
maybe some sort of subtitle.
It looks like I have a
couple of numbers right here,
and there's some buttons.
My guess is, these three buttons
are probably pretty important
because they're nice and bold.
And then I can tell that I also
have this little repeating multiple
of a chart bouncing across here.
Now, every example is gonna
be a little bit different
but I would say that finding
an individual action,
adding a new action and
publishing an unpublished profile
are gonna be some of the
most important things
that you could do on this page.
So the fact that those
things and the title
and the subtitle and these
kind of key indicators
are the first things you
see in that squint test,
that is a good sign.
A squint test is kind of
a final check of saying,
all right, if I think I've
gotten everything good
to go here.
Can I be sure that this design is going
to corral my users' attention effectively?
All right, now I just wanna
end with a few final thoughts
on the color gray.
The first is gray is
the most subtle color.
This is something we've
kind of alluded to already,
but gray attracts no
undue attention to itself.
Because of that, It's the perfect color
to let the other content
on the page, shine through.
It's the perfect color for
those kind of meta content
like elements, the background
colors, the divider lines,
the shadows, even some of the text.
The more gray you have, the
more you're allowing yourself
freedom to direct attention
effectively using color.
The next point is that
gray allows the content
to shine through.
Of course, this is kind of
connected to the first point
but I wanna show you
some specific examples.
Again, let's take a look
at a site like Dribbble.
If you go to a site like Dribbble,
the focus is absolutely on
this content right here.
Thee uploads by designers
who are part of the site,
consequently almost everything else
on the entire screen is gray.
Like they have some
imagery for your team logo
or your personal profile photo.
There's some pink links right here.
Of course there's a big
button that is supposed
to attract my attention.
This is them, corralling our attention
towards uploading a shot,
which they would like us to do.
But other than that, it's basically gray
kind of taking a back seat to the content.
YouTube is another perfect example
of the same sort of thing.
If I look for color on this screen
it's like just in the videos,
it's just in the content,
the images and whatever.
And there's basically no pops of color.
In fact, looking around, I kind
of only see it in this home.
So again, a selected state
and in a logo right here.
Right now we're looking
at this in the context
of a light design but
I can also go and say,
use a dark theme.
And this whole lesson is
applicable to dark themes as well.
Now we have a totally
separate video on that.
And so we'll be talking about
it later, but just consider
that a dark theme as well is gonna really
let that content shine through
and rather than competing
with it, with white, which
is also a very bright color.
We're basically saying
nothing on the screen,
has any real saturation or brightness
except for the content.
You wanna talk about letting
the content shine through.
And that's what dark
themes can really excel at.
And finally, gray is
also the classiest color.
There is a undeniable connection
between the color gray
and creating a luxury brand.
And I think this is because
gray is understated.
When you're selling
something that's luxury
or really expensive.
You want all attention
to go to the imagery,
whatever these highly stylized videos
of super expensive
earrings or whatever it is.
So as I scroll down, I'm
looking at a lot of black.
Again, this is kind of like a
dark theme, at least in places
a lot of high quality
imagery, but even fewer pops
of color than I otherwise might have.
I collected some luxury
like shots on Dribbble
and I'll link to these below,
but you can get an idea
that you're just gonna end up seeing a ton
of black and white.
It's those understated colors that truly
let thee content shine through.
And that covers it for the color gray.
So take a look at the homework
below as you go through it.
Remember all the tips that
we've talked about today
and as you apply the
lessons from this video
to your design work.
I encourage you really to think
about black and white first.
Again, I don't say this is
something that you need to stick
to a hundred percent of the time,
but until you feel quite
comfortable with color.
It's really not a bad idea
to try and nail those fundamental
elements of the design,
before you start adding on
too many splashes of color.
You will have a lot of time
to get better at color.
Once you have nailed the
foundations involved with gray
and all the things that we've
talked about up to this point.
All right, so take a look at the homework.
Lemme know if you have any questions,
we'll see you in the next lesson.